Hi all,
today, we'll be covering the details -
of working as a team online
and how you might conduct standups.
Just note that the we won't be covering all -
aspects of group work in this tutorial.
Although standups are an efficient way of conducting -
meetings, you should still conduct -
longer meetings that are purely focused on -
the actual project writing and analysis.
Today, we'll be going through: Early Planning -
and Meeting Minutes,
some examples of online tools,
and the basics of standups and kanban.
After this section, we'll also have -
a mock standup run by your fellow tutors!
So, Early Planning and Meeting Minutes.
This step is strongly recommended for -
groups to do in their very first official meeting -
or as soon as possible.
For "early planning", your team -
should write down (in writing) -
about the allocation of tasks -
and responsibilities.
Your team must also -
all agree in writing.
For example,
with everyone's full name and dates -
to make sure it is agreed upon.
(kind of like how you might sign a contract)
The initial plan is flexible,
but should serve as a general guideline -
that your team can follow throughout -
the project's timeline.
And of course, if things need to be adjusted -
and changed, they can be.
(So long as your team is happy with it and they sign it off)
This initial plan combined with your -
minutes will serve as important -
evidence if there are any -
disagreements over contribution or workload.
Here's an example of a very basic Early Plan.
As you can see,
we have the list of group members and -
a brief outline of each members' task -
allocation and commitments.
What are meeting minutes?
Well, they're dot point summaries -
of what happened in the meeting.
And if the meeting was long or detailed,
then these minutes should summaries -
these additional notes as well.
Here's an example of a meeting minute.
We have the time and members who attended,
as well as a dot point summary -
of the agenda that was covered.
It's supposed to be short, brief, and easy to read.
Now to the next section.
Online Collaboration Tools.
In terms of writing a report out collaboratively,
you should aim to use tools such as:
a shared Google doc or -
or Office or Overleaf
(if you're comfortable learning or using Latex)
...and this is the one I recommend.
Overleaf is a free online platform -
which allows live collaboration for latex reports.
Latex is a markup language -
(much like HTML and markdown)
and is the most common way -
of writing up reports in industry -
or for research.
In fact,
many of your assignments and -
lecture slides that you get at the -
university, are actually written in Latex.
Now, in terms of keeping track -
of your teams progress between the -
standups, there are a plethora -
of communication and collaborative -
tools, such as:
Discord or Slack,
Online spreadsheets,
your Canvas Group Page,
checking Git Commits and Issues,
and finally, Kanban boards
(which we will cover in a bit)
We will now introduce the concepts of -
a standup, which is an -
"agile" work methodology that -
that industry teams follow when -
working from home or working remotely.
Especially during COVID, where -
many businesses have transitioned into the -
working from home (WFH) lifestyle,
important that you have some experience -
and at least an attempt at -
maintaining some form of online team work using standups.
This will not only be beneficial for your -
university projects, but will also -
serve as an important skill that you -
chuck down on your resume -
or discuss during your interview.
So, Part 3.
Standups and Kanban.
So, what is a standup?
In many American sports such -
as football and rugby,
the team has a huddle before each play.
The huddle is short and strategic.
It keeps the team informed,
connected,
and calibrated throughout the game.
For software teams,
the standup is much like a team's huddle,
and we usually refer to this as a "scrum meeting".
In other words,
scrums are a daily meeting that -
involves the core team; such as your -
project managers,
your clients, and developers.
For your group project,
this will just be all the team members.
Although standups can vary -
across different teams and corporations,
we usually have 3 very simple questions -
that each person takes in turns to answer.
1. What work have I completed since the last standup?
2. What new tasks can I work on until the next standup?
and 3. What issues came across that are blocking my progress?
Standups are supposed to be kept short and efficient,
so each person usually spends -
no more than a couple minutes talking.
Hence a standup,
you stand up and give a short talk.
It's also strongly recommended -
that you have someone on rotation -
every standup to write your meeting minute,
so you don't have to "remember" or "make them up" later.
Kanban Boards.
Now that we have covered the basics -
of a standup,
let’s move onto Kanban boards -
within the context of Agile work methodology.
Kanban, is actually a Japanese term -
for billboard.
And in the context of Agile,
Kanban boards have tasks that are -
represented visually as a card on the board,
allowing all team members to see the -
progress of each task at any time.
Now, to the right here, you can see -
an example of a kanban board with -
several tasks and cards.
There are usually 4 cards,
but here, we also have a 5th card for -
"URGENT" which denotes a task -
that needs to be completed as soon as possible.
Now going through this, you'll -
notice we have a "TODO" section.
These tasks here, such as -
Report Error Analysis, Report Discussion,
these have yet to be started.
"In Progress", we've got -
a couple tasks here;
such as Visualization,
Report Methodology,
Initial Results,
these are tasks that are currently -
being completed.
And "URGENT", these tasks -
must be completed -
as soon as possible.
It usually means there's a deadline or -
other tasks rely on this one -
to be completed.
And finally, we've got "BLOCKED".
These, are a list of tasks -
where you cannot start them -
until another task has finished.
And there we go,
"COMPLETED" on the side, where these -
are just a list of your completed tasks.
In a Kanban board, tasks -
are broken down into four main categories.
Tasks to do,
tasks in progress,
tasks that are blocked,
and tasks that are completed.
Whenever you generate tasks in a standup,
you add them to "to do".
When you start your task,
you move that task to "in progress".
And if your task is "blocked" by -
someone else,
for example, it relies on another -
person to finish their task,
then you move it to "blocked" .
That is, your tasks' progress is
blocked until the prerequisite task is completed.
When you finish your task, you can -
then add it to "completed" .
Kanban boards can be make-shift,
so you can use existing tools such as;
Google Sheets,
your Group Space in Canvas,
or Atlassian's JIRA, which is -
what we'll be using in today's mock standup.
You can also use a physical -
whiteboard or wall, and have -
sticky notes and move them physically.
(if that's how you would like to do it)
Now that we've gone through all the foundational concepts,
let's go into a mock example of a tri-weekly standup with a Kanban board.